Good morning. Today's דף *daf* is ל"ג *lamed gimmel* where we're still
catching up a little bit on ל"ב עמוד amud ב׳ *lamed bet
amud bet*. אמר רב אשי amar Rav Ashi, *Amar Rav Ashi*, it
is about three-ten lines from the top, end of the line. The
line starts with אפילו הכי הידור Hiddur מעבד ליה בעי *afilu hachi
hiddur me'avad leh ba'ei*. Okay, so this is the whole question about
about can a רב rav *rav* be מוחל mochel *mochel* on his
כבוד kavod. *kavod*? Can a father be מוחל mochel *mochel* on his
כבוד kavod, *kavod*? The answer is yes. Can a רב rav, *rav*
be מוחל mochel *mochel* on his כבוד kavod *kavod*? That was somewhat
debated because the רבי Rebbe *rebbe* is representing the כבוד kavod. *kavod*
of the תורה Torah, *Torah*. And maybe even if he doesn't mind
personally, people have to show him respect because otherwise it would be
it would be disrespecting the תורה Torah *Torah* that he represents. And
nevertheless the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* concludes which is actually a very powerful
statement about the nature of תורה Torah שבעל פה *Torah Sheba'al Peh*
and the personal relationship and investment that it becomes your תורה Torah
*Torah*. So you actually have an identification with it and an ownership
with it, which in an interesting and a fascinating way doesn't just
mean you can stake your claim and your connection, but it also
puts you in a position to be say I'm okay if you
don't sort of show me, you know, כבוד kavod *kavod*, even though
I'm also representing תורה Torah *Torah* which demands כבוד kavod. *kavod*. So
but because I now have an ownership stake in it. And the
conclusion of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was that even after רב *Rav*
is מוחל mochel *mochel* on his כבוד kavod *kavod*, okay, people should
still do some type of a sign of respect. So that was
the last line we left off with yesterday. אפילו הידור Hiddur מעבד
ליה בעי *afilu hiddur me'avad leh ba'ei*. They should have shown him
some form of הדרת *hadarta*, right? Here we'd be talking כבוד kavod.
*kavod* but we're going to get to the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of
והדרת פני זקן zaken. *vehadarta pnei zaken*, which is honor to an
older person, which is interpreted as honor to a sage is how
it's going to be interpreted. So they still have to do some
sign of respect. רמב"ם *Rambam* leaves it generic as they have to
show him הידור Hiddur, *hiddur*. He says you could be מוחל mochel
*mochel* on your כבוד kavod, *kavod* and technically they're exempt, but they're
still obligated, they're like exempt and obligated. They still have a need
to demonstrate some form of respect. And רש"י Rashi *Rashi* actually says
לנוע מעט כאילו רוצה לעמוד מפניו *linua me'at ke'ilu rotze la'amod mipanav*.
So if anybody's ever been to the ישיבה yeshiva *yeshiva* and knows
the whole thing about like, you know, the tush move, which is
like, you know, you sort of wave your tush a little halfway
off the seat or whatever, that actually according to רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here is saying. That even if
the רבי Rebbe *rebbe* doesn't, you know, doesn't want everybody to stand
fully for them, that might be it's actually striking this balance. It's
enough his תורה Torah *Torah* that he can be מוחל mochel *mochel*
on the full sign of respect, but at the end of the
day, whatever he's מוחל mochel *mochel* or not, he still represents תורה
Torah *Torah*. And you can't allow somebody who represents תורה Torah *Torah*
to not have any respect, any sign of respect shown towards that
person. And this embodies that balance. It demands respect, but it's clear
that he's מוחל mochel *mochel*, so it does not have to be
the full amount. And that's the sort of conclusion of the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. אמר רב אשי
*Amar Rav Ashi*, says רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, אפילו למאן דאמר רב
שמחל על כבודו כבודו מחול *afilu leman de'amar rav shemachal al kevodo,
kevodo machul*. Even if the one who says that his כבוד kavod,
*kavod* is, you know, forgiven, is waived, the honor, he can waive
the honor, but נשיא Nasi. שמחל על כבודו אין כבודו מחול *nasi
shemachal al kevodo ein kevodo machul*. A person who is a נשיא
Nasi *nasi*, which is like the prince but it meant a very
specific role of the exilarch in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, which was
an interesting combination by the way of both political leadership and rabbinic
leadership, which was the role that רבי Rebbe יהודה הנשיא *Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi* played and his descendants. In בבל *Bavel* they were separated, right?
There was there was not a somebody who was both a political
and a religious head, but in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* there was.
That person cannot be מוחל mochel *mochel* on his כבוד kavod *kavod*.
So it could be the combination of the two, political and religious
leadership, but it seems that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is making more
of a shift and contrast to the specific issue of political leadership.
That and we'll see about that in a minute, that there's a
need of, you know, this also does fit into the whole כיבוד
אב ואם *kibbud av va'em* issue in general, which the which the
issue of כיבוד רב *kibbud rav* does and the idea of מלך
melech *melech*. All of these are institutions of authority. So, you know,
you have to there's God, you know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* compared
it to honor of God, honor of parents, honor of תורה Torah
*Torah* or honor of a רבי Rebbe *rebbi*. That the idea of
society has these institutions of authority which are central to the way
it sort of, you know, it's structured, and that's important to be
to be acknowledged and respected. So it seems that the issue here
about the נשיא Nasi *nasi* is that even if there's some degree
that individuals can waive that honor due to them, right? Nevertheless, like
the institution of the fundamental institution of authority, right? That you're subject
to the rules of the land and you know to the to
the leader of the land and so on, you know, that fundamentally
is too deep of a demand in terms of the society, you
know, what that represents in terms of the society, that no that
a person cannot choose to be like מוחל mochel, *mochel* on that.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says continuing with that theme,
let's take a look. מיתיבי *Meisive*, I'll ask you on this. מיתיבי
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua ורבי צדוק שהיו מסובין
בבית המשתה *Meisive Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbi Yehoshua, Rabbi Tzadok shehayu mesubbin beveis
hamishteh* that all these rabbis were were reclining and eating in this
in the wedding feast, or whatever, in a in some type of
a בית המשתה *beis hamishteh*. בהילולי בנו של רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
*B'hilulei bno shel Rabban Gamliel*, the son of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
*Rabban Gamliel*. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* was the נשיא Nasi.
*nasi*. והיה רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel עומד ומשקה עליהם *Vehayah Rabban Gamliel
omaid umashkeh aleihem*. And רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* was there pouring the
drinks. We've seen from the previous stories that apparently that... That's something
that the host would do. But even if it's something that the
host would do, nevertheless it's a degree of מחילה mechila on their
כבוד. kavod If you're holding by your honor, then you're not the
one pouring drinks for somebody else. נתן הכוס לרבי אליעזר ולא נטלו.
Nasan hakos l'Rabbi Eliezer v'lo natlo. He gave the כוס kos to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer refused to accept
it. And as we're going to see, he refused to accept it
because he said it's not appropriate for me to accept the service
of the
נשיא. Nasi, So even if it's not even just inferring from this
action that we can therefore not show him respect elsewhere, even in
the very action in which he is being מוחל mochel in his
כבוד, kavod, I cannot participate in that.
I cannot allow the נשיא nassi to play this type of subservient
role towards me. He's the one that has to be held in
the higher esteem.
So נתנה לרבי יהושע, nasnah l'Rabbi Yehoshua, so then רבן גמליאל gave
the cup to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua וקבלו v'kiblo and he accepted
it. אמר לו רבי אליעזר, Amar lo Rabbi Eliezer, so רבי Rebbe
אליעזר said, מה זה יהושע? mah zeh Yehoshua? What is this you're
doing, יהושע? Yehoshua? אנו יושבים ורבן גמליאל עומד ומשקה עלינו? Anu yoshvim
v'Rabban Gamliel omeid umashkeh aleinu? We should sit and have רבן גמליאל
the נשיא nassi coming and serving and attending to us? That's not
appropriate, even if he's willing to do it we shouldn't be willing
to do it. אמר ליה, Amar ley, so רבי Rebbe יהושע said
back to him, מצינו גדול ממנו ששימש. matzinu gadol mimenu sheshimash. No,
we've seen one even greater than him who served. אברהם, Avraham, I
just want to read the parentheses, אברהם גדול ממנו ושימש. Avraham gadol
mimenu v'shimash. אברהם Avraham was greater than him and he attended to
his guests. אברהם גדול הדור היה. Avraham gadol hador hayah. He was
the great of the generation. וכתיב בו, u'chtiv bo, והוא עומד עליהם.
v'hu omeid aleihem. He was standing over them, over the angels and
serving them. ושמא תאמרו כמלאכי השרת נדמו לו? V'shema tomru k'malachei hashareis
nidmu lo? Maybe it's because he knew they were angels? No, כערביים
נדמו לו, k'arviyim nidmu lo,
he appeared to them like Arabs.
ואנו לא יהא רבן גמליאל ברבי עומד ומשקה עלינו? V'anu lo yehei
Rabban Gamliel b'Rebbi omeid umashkeh aleinu? We won't have רבן גמליאל there
and attending to us and pouring us drinks? Now of course a
difference could be made. אברהם Avraham was a גדול הדור, gadol hador,
it didn't mean he was a נשיא. nassi It does get to
the question of what is the type of, it's not just how
great a person is, but if it's specifically about the role of
holding political authority, then that was not a reality with אברהם. Avraham.
But anyway that was the response he
had to certainly the political authority of the house of אברהם. Avraham.
That's true. But then you could say that it could also be
true about אדם שמחל על כבודו adam shemachal al kevodo within his
house.
That was the whole עם ישראל Am Yisrael then. That was the
whole body of Israel.
I see, you don't mean physically that, you mean the household like
he represented the head of the clan of Israel. I see that.
That's an interesting point. Of course the people that he was attending
to were not part of his
clan, it's also not an exact comparison. Anyway,
אמר להם רבי צדוק, amar lahem Rabbi Tzadok, רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok
said to he was sitting there among them,
עד מתי אתם מניחים כבודו של מקום ואתם עוסקים בכבוד הבריות? Ad
masai atem manichim kevodo shel Makom v'atem oskim bichvod habriyos? Obviously there's
a little irony here because we're talking about being מוחל mochal on
the כבוד kavod, and is that acceptable or not? And he's saying
actually by using the example of אברהם Avraham you are actually giving
an ironically more respect, you're being מוחל on God's כבוד. kavod, You're
more respect to אברהם Avraham and using him as the example when
you should be using God as the example. Why should you be
using God as the example? הקדוש ברוך הוא, Hakadosh Baruch Hu, think
about what God does. משיב רוחות ומעלה נשיאים Meshiv ruchos u'ma'aleh nesi'im
because of the winds to blow and the clouds to rise from
the ground ומוריד מטר u'morid matar brings the rain down ומצמיח
אדמה u'matzmiach adamah causes the ground to sprout forth ועורך שולחן לפני
כל אחד ואחד v'oreich shulchan lifnei kol echad v'echad
and God lays out the table like he prepares the food for
every creature. Think about God, he's the farmer and he waters the
crops and harvest whatever he does all this work to make everybody
have their food. So if God provides for every human being, אנו
לא יהא רבן גמליאל ברבי עומד ומשקה עלינו? anu lo yehei Rabban
Gamliel b'Rebbi omeid umashkeh aleinu? We can't let him just serve us
and attend to us?
So anyway, so there they use that as example. God certainly is
the example of political
authority, and nevertheless that's not a compromise to God's authority. Now the
interesting thing about this is, is that then an evidence that you
can be מוחל on your כבוד kavod. or is that saying this
is not an act of מחילת כבוד? mechilas kavod? That actually, A,
because רבן גמליאל is sort of being like God, והלכת בדרכיו, v'halachta
bidrachav, he's acting in a way that's God-like to take care of
people's needs, or maybe it's saying that when somebody takes care of
the needs of people below him, that's not be interpreted as a
מחילה of the כבוד. kavod. There's other things maybe that are מוחל
of כבוד kavod but this isn't one of them. This you can
allow yourself to be served. So again, it's not an exact comparison.
A, is the אברהם Avraham exactly comparable to the idea of נשיא,
nassi although Ido makes a very good point in terms of the
head of the אברהם Avraham clan, but also the question could be
what types of things you interpret as a compromise of כבוד. kavod,
Okay, it seems that the whole point is this does not compromise
somebody's כבוד, kavod, which is a different question than if somebody says
it's okay to do something that compromises on my כבוד, can you,
can you go ahead and do it? Right? Anyway, but the גמרא
Gemara takes this as evidence, thank you, that a רב can be,
that a נשיא nasi, can be מוחל על כבודו, mochel al kvodo,
and the גמרא Gemara concludes, אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר, ela i
itmar hachi itmar, if it was said, here's how it was said:
אמר רב אשי, אפילו מאן דאמר נשיא שמחל על כבודו כבודו מחול,
afilu man de'amar nassi shemachal al kvodo kvodo machul, even the one
who says a נשיא nasi, who waives his honor, his honor is
waived, מלך שמחל על כבודו אין כבודו מחול, melech shemachal al kvodo
ein kvodo machul, a king cannot.
Okay. שנאמר, shenemar, שום תשים עליך מלך, som tasim alecha melech, שתהא
אימתו עליך, shedei ein maso alecha, you shall place upon you a
king, the sense of upon you means that it like has to
be always over you, and therefore the king's fear has to constantly
be over you. And again, you could sort of speak about, you
know, the benefit of the society of having the sense of the
sense of the of law and order and that's not something that
can be violated and you cannot treat the authorities, you know, lightly
and so on. So you know, there's like obviously, like, you know,
even in aren't there like special,
you know, prison terms and sentences for people that, you know, like
assault a cop, right, as opposed to assaulting, you know, somebody else,
right? What? MTA worker. MTA worker, right. Really? Okay, so you know,
you need certain people, like, so you know, that cannot be compromised,
right? It's like when they say in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, you
know, you should always be מתפלל לשלומה של מלכות, mitpallel lishloma shel
malchut, because if it was not for the fear of the government,
like everybody would, you know, it would be anarchy, you know, everybody
would consume their neighbor. Right? So it's deeply necessary for society that
that not be compromised. And again, maybe the idea that נשיא was
different was that maybe that was a little bit more, you know,
persuasion than authority. Anyway, it's interesting why exactly, you know, what if
it's because it's connected to תורה, Torah but you know, נשיא is
different and מלך is that is something that cannot be compromised. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues, תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, now that
we've discussed כבוד of the רב, but we haven't really mentioned the
biblical basis for that. So we're now going to turn to the
פסוקים psukim that serve as the as the basis for this. Let's
take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, מפני שיבה תקום והדרת פני
זקן ויראת מאלוקיך אני
השם, mipnei seiva takum vehadarta pnei zaken veyareta me'elokecha ani Hashem, right,
that before the hoary head you shall rise up, and you shall
show honor to the elderly, I am God. So that's going to
turn into, it sounds like, respect of people of old age, which
will be a debate, but it's going to turn into, most immediately,
respect of a תורה Torah sage. Okay, so יכול אפילו מפני זקן
אשמאי, yachol afilu mipnei zaken ashmai,
maybe it means even an elder who רש"י Rashi, says is a
wicked elder, but תוספות Tosafot says more neutrally, just a elder who's
an ignorant elder, like a non-scholar, a non-sage, you know, some illiterate
elder, תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, זקן. zaken. So it says at the
end, it starts with שיבה, seiva, which emphasizes the age, you know,
white-haired. But then it says זקן. zaken זקן zaken means something else.
ואין זקן אלא חכם. ve'ein zaken ela chacham. זקן zaken, means a
sage. שנאמר, shenemar, אספה לי שבעים איש מזקני ישראל, asfa li shivim
ish miziknei Yisrael,
and the end of the פסוק pasuk. is שהם מה בסוף הפסוק
shehem mah besof hapasuk אספה לי
שבעים איש מזקני ישראל asfa li shivim ish miziknei Yisrael חכמי ישראל
מה זה
chachmei Yisrael
mah
zeh
אשר ידעת כי הם asher yadata ki hem
something. Now I'm blanking on the end of the פסוק. pasuk.
במדבר י"א. Bamidbar yud-alef. מזקני העם ושוטריו? miziknei ha'am veshotrav?
Okay,
so, really? But then זקן, zaken no, that, ושוטריו, veshotrav,
how would that show you that they're חכמים? chachamim? Hold on. שוטריו
veshotrav
is חכמים? chachamim? במדבר י"א, Bamidbar yud-alef,
אשר ידעת כי הם זקני
העם ושוטריו.
asher yadata
ki hem ziknei ha'am veshotrav.
Oh, אשר ידעת, asher yadata,
because if it was just about being old, then it wouldn't be
that you know. Aha, that could be. אספה לי שבעים איש מזקני
ישראל אשר ידעת כי הם זקני העם ושוטריו, asfa li shivim ish
miziknei Yisrael asher yadata ki hem ziknei ha'am veshotrav, yeah. Alright, but
maybe you're right, maybe it's אשר ידעת. asher yadata. So somehow that
signifies that they are not just old, but hold positions of authority
and maybe of wisdom and knowledge. Okay. So therefore זקן zaken means
also a sage. And therefore even שיבה seiva means a sage. So
it's not about the elderly, it's about the sage. רבי יוסי הגלילי
אומר, Rabbi Yosei HaGelili omer, אין זקן אלא מי שקנה חכמה. ein
zaken ela mi shekanah chochmah. זקן zaken. means somebody who acquired wisdom,
and רש"י Rashi says it's actually a play on words, זה קנה,
zeh kanah, this one acquired, קנה, kanah, acquired wisdom. So it means
a sage.
שנאמר, shenemar, השם קנני ראשית דרכו, Hashem kanani reishit darko, the emphasis
on קנין. kinyan. God has
possessed me or created me the first of God's paths.
יכול יעמוד מפניו ממקום רחוק, yachol ya'amod mipanav mimakom rachok,
maybe you should stand up when he's far away? תלמוד לומר, talmud
lomar,
תקום והדרת, takum vehadarta, you shall rise and you shall show honor.
the white-haired and to honor to the elderly. Now what we're going
to do is, but you could have said, oh, there're two different
categories: there're people maybe that are old that you rise before מפני
שיבה seivah, תקום *mi-pnei seiva takum* and there're people that are זקן
zaken *zaken* that are Torah sages that you do something else called
הידור hiddur *hiddur*. You could have said that. But what we're going
to do is we're going to conflate everything. We're going to say,
no, זקן zaken? *zaken* really illustrates what שיבה seivah *seiva* is, and
we're only talking about Torah sages. And והדרת *ve-hadarta* illustrates what תקום
*takum* means, and we're really all talking about one type of person
and one type of action. Okay, so we're conflating everything. So maybe
standing up is from a distance. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar, תקום והדרת
Takum v'hadarta. *talmud lomar takum ve-hadarta*, we read those two words together.
I'm sorry, I skipped. לא lo, אמרתי קימה Kima אלא במקום שיש
הידור hiddur *lo amarti kima ela be-makom she-yesh hiddur*. קימה Kima *kima*
is in a way that shows honoring. If you stand up when
the person is a hundred feet away, that's not the same honoring
as when the person moves directly into your, like we're going to
see later, ארבע אמות arba amot. *arba amot* directly into your zone
and you stand up for them, that's a much greater show of
honor and respect. יכול יעמוד מפניו *yakhol yaamod mi-panav*? Okay, so קימה
Kima *kima* is modified by והדרת *ve-hadarta*. Now let's look at it
the other way. Does והדרת *ve-hadarta* exist
independent of קימה kima *kima*? Is there a way you show honor
and respect, you know, without standing up? Maybe it means that you
honor the person by lavishing them with gifts? Okay, maybe that's the
והדרת *ve-hadarta*. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar תקום והדרת *talmud lomar takum ve-hadarta*.
מה קימה kimah שאין בה חסרון כיס chisron kis, *ma kima she-ein
ba chisron kis*, the same way rising up is a way is
nothing that costs you any money, אף הידור hiddur שאין בו חסרון
כיס *af hiddur she-ein bo chisron kis*. It's a way of showing
respect; it's not maybe limited to rising, how you talk to them,
you know, other forms of demonstrating your respect for them, but not
something about lavishing them with gifts, not something that costs you any
money. Okay, so now we have תקום *takum* is modified by והדרת
*ve-hadarta*, it's a rising that shows respect. והדרת *ve-hadarta* is modified by
תקום *takum*, there are other ways you show respect, but they don't
have to be ways of spending money. Okay, now יכול יעמוד מפניו
מבית הכיסא ומבית המרחץ *yakhol yaamod mi-panav mi-beit ha-kise u-mi-beit ha-merchatz*? Maybe
if you're in the bathhouse, you have to stand up when a
Torah sage enters? Okay, תלמוד לומר תקום והדרת *talmud lomar takum ve-hadarta*.
Again, והדרת *ve-hadarta* is modifying תקום *takum*. לא lo, אמרתי קימה אלא
במקום שיש הידור hiddur *lo amarti kima ela be-makom she-yesh hiddur*, in
a place where it's sort of a certain,
you know, הידור hiddur *hiddur* is a societal, I mean, look, there
could be issues where nobody is around and you don't talk to
somebody in a disrespectful way which doesn't have to do with how
it's sort of positioned within society, it's just totally interpersonal. But nevertheless,
הידור hiddur *hiddur* to a large degree is also a sort of
a societal reality, right? About, you know, so in a certain type
of a societal context in which an act would be sort of
like, you know, like, I'll tell you another הלכה Halacha *halakha*. ההלכה
היא שאין מכבדין בבית הכיסא *ha-halakha hi she-ein mechabdin be-beit ha-kise*, right?
So you walk, you know, you go to the bathroom and you
come at the same time with your רבי Rebbe *rebbe*, you say,
"No, no, you go first." So, you know, which you could say,
I don't know, it doesn't seem totally absurd to me. But at
a certain point it's like at that sort of, in that context,
where everybody is somewhat, you know, reduced
to their most sort of
fundamental human nature,
you know, very, and therefore it's not about societal standing and position
that exists within that context. So therefore that's not an appropriate place
to be showing respect. I guess there's greater equality there. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, תלמוד לומר לא אמרתי קימה אלא במקום שיש
הידור *talmud lomar lo amarti kima ela be-makom she-yesh hiddur*. יכול יעצים
עיניו מפניו שלא יראהו *yakhol yaatzim einav mi-panav she-lo yirehu*? Maybe you
should close your eyes, pretend you don't see him? Okay, and as
long as I didn't see him, I don't have to rise before
him. תלמוד לומר תקום ויראת talmud lomar takum v'yareisa. *talmud lomar takum
ve-yareta*. Yeah, the end of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, מפני שיבה תקום
והדרת Mipnei seiva takum v'hadarta, פני זקן ויראת zaken v’yareita, מאלוקיך *mi-pnei
seiva takum ve-hadarta pnei zaken ve-yareta me-elokecha*, you should fear God. So
why do you have to fear God? Everybody can see whether you're
showing respect or not. So it's to show you דבר המסור ללב
*davar ha-masur la-lev*, something that is only something that God could know.
So if you're closing your eyes and pretending you don't see him,
then God knows that you do see him; obviously you've done something
wrong. Okay, נאמר בו ויראת מאלוקיך *ne-emar bo ve-yareta me-elokecha*, so only
something that is given over to the heart is there something that
you have to fear God about. רב שמעון בן אלעזר אומר *Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar omer*: מניין לזקן שלא יטריח *minayin le-zaken she-lo yatriach*?
How do you know that the זקן zaken *zaken* has a responsibility
not to cause, like not to make other people have to bear
the burden of showing him respect? That he should try
to minimize the responsibility on other people. תלמוד לומר זקן ויראת talmud
lomar zaken veyarata. *talmud lomar zaken ve-yareta*, the elder person has to
fear God. And we're going to see that means is like you
don't necessarily, you know, you maybe if you can walk in a
way that you don't have to walk into a crowded room and
everybody's going to have to stand before you, so better to avoid
that, right? Which is an interesting compromise from the earlier discussion about
being מוחל על כבודו *mochel al kevodo*. This isn't being מוחל על
כבודו *mochel al kevodo*, it's just understanding that why not putting people
in a position that they have to be forced to do this
for me? Okay. איסי בן יהודה Isi ben Yehuda אומר *Issi ben
Yehuda omer* says: מפני שיבה seivah? תקום *mi-pnei seiva takum*, אפילו כל
שיבה seivah במשמע *afilu kol seiva be-mashma*. He says, no, שיבה seivah
*seiva* means... any person of white hair, any older person. It is
a respect of old age. It's not limited to respect of sages.
Okay. So that's the end of the ברייתא. braita, Now the גמרא
Gemara goes back. So in terms of who's included, we have the
first position that says elders, you know, wise men, sages, because it
says אלו שבעים מזקני ישראל. eilu shivim miziknei yisrael. That was the,
then we have רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGlili who says מי
שקנה חכמה, mi shekanah chochmah, which sounds to be the same idea.
And then you have, what's his name, you have איסי בן יהודה
Isi ben Yehuda. who says it even includes just an older person,
period. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
רבי יוסי הגלילי היינו תנא קמא, Rabbi Yosei HaGlili hainu Tanna Kamma,
isn't רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGlili who quotes the, who says
זה קנה חכמה zeh kanah chochmah the same as the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma who says זקני ישראל? ziknei yisrael? גמרא Gemara says no.
איכא בינייהו יניק וחכים. ika beinaihu yanik vechakim. The difference is when
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that you have to be a
sage, he's saying that in addition to being a, you know, an
elderly person, you know, so therefore it's like it's not enough that
you're שיבה, seivah you also have to be a sage. It's an
older person who is a sage. But if you have a young
person who is a sage, for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that's
not obligated in respect. תנא קמא סבר יניק וחכים, Tanna Kamma savar
yanik vechakim, a young person who's a sage, לא, is not obligated,
it's only שיבה seivah plus
זקן. zaken ורבי יוסי הגלילי סבר, v’Rabbi Yosei HaGlili savar, no, even
just having, you know, great wisdom and knowledge, that suffices.
מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי הגלילי? mai ta’ama d’Rabbi Yosei HaGlili? Why does
he say that זקן zaken, is enough without the שיבה? seivah? אמר
לך, amar lach, I'll tell you, אי סלקא דעתך כדאמר תנא קמא,
ei salka da’atach k’d’amar Tanna Kamma, if you think like it's like
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says, אם כן נכתוב רחמנא מפני שיבה
זקן תקום והדרת. im kein nichtov rachmana mipnei seivah zaken takum vehadarta.
Just combine them all, say from a, you know, elderly sage you
should rise up and show honor. מאי שנא דפלגינהו רחמנא? mai shna
d’palgineihu rachmana? Why did the תורה Torah separate שיבה seivah from זקן?
zaken למימרא דהאי לאו האי והאי לאו האי, l’meimra d’hai lav hai
v’hai lav hai, to tell you that they're separate categories. Now of
course if they're separate categories, you would think logically that he would
also say that somebody who's just old and not a sage, either
one suffices, which is a very reasonable read of the פסוק. But
both רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say, and then he also is
the position of this who, this איסי בן יהודה. Isi ben Yehuda.
רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot for various reasons recognize that that's a
reasonable read of the גמרא Gemara but they resist that read. They
somehow say according to him, well once we've separated them, we understand
that זקן zaken is enough by itself, just to be a sage.
And once זקן Zaken is enough to be a sage just by
itself, that's what שיבה seivah means. So at the end of the
day, they are just one category, but they're one category that gets
sort of reduced to זקן, Zaken you know, שיבה Seiva, doesn't mean
anything for him. Okay, so that's the way רש״י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot say, although reasonably you could read it that there's two categories:
elderly and sage, and each one is completely independent of the other.
But the חכמים Chachamim say you have to have both. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says
שמע מינה אפילו יניק וחכים, shma mina afilu yanik vechakim, even young
and a sage, that's for רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yosei HaGlili. ותנא
קמא? v’Tanna Kamma? And the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would say משום
דבעי למיסמך זקן ויראת. mishum d’baei lemismach zaken v’yareita. No, no, no,
it had to separate them because it wanted to say זקן zaken
ויראת, right, which is the דרשה drasha that the elderly person, the
sage should not, you know, make people have to, you know, be,
you know, make people go out of their way to show him
honor. So that's why it had to split them up. But fundamentally,
you have both criteria: elderly and a sage. That is for the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, whereas רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGlili says
the sage aspect is enough by itself.
Okay, so by the way תוספות Tosafot does want to say that
according to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGlili he is bothered, which
is if it's not that there're really two completely separate categories, elderly
on one hand and sage on the other, if fundamentally it's just
about being a sage, why did the תורה Torah say שיבה Seiva
all together according to רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yosei HaGlili, right? According
to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma you need both. You need somebody
to be old and to be a sage. According to רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGlili if it's all about being a sage, why
does the תורה Torah mention שיבה? And תוספות Tosafot basically says well
here's the difference: you get some points for being older. So older
is not enough to demand that the person gets shown respect, they
have to be a תורה Torah sage. But let's say somebody's, I
don't know, an average תורה Torah sage, not a big תלמיד חכם.
talmid chacham. So if you've got an average תורה Torah sage and
they're older, then they're in the שיבה category. If you have somebody
that's a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and young, then they're in
the זקן zaken category. Okay, but if you've got somebody that's an
average תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and young, they don't get, you don't
have to show them respect. Or if somebody's not a תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham at all and they're old, they don't get respect. Okay,
so it's like a point system. But the minimum requirement is you
have to be a תורה Torah sage. Okay, you have to be
a תורה Torah? sage plus you need some extra points. So either
the extra points are because you're a big תורה Torah. sage, or
the extra points are because you're old. Okay, but there's a minimum
level of תורה Torah knowledge to get you started. That's the way
תוספות Tosafot explains why for רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGlili there's
a שיבה category and a זקן zaken category. Okay, and according to
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma you need the two of them combined.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
But what were you going to say?
Well, it's a kind of an implicit understanding that one's life
experience—right, so that's going to be the question later, right? Is it
that because somebody's older, they—meaning is it really that זקן means when
we say the town elders, right, it means yes it means that
they're older but it's also presumed to be leaders and people who
are like not just random old people? Right, so specific. Normally the
word elders has the does have that connotation of both, right? Knowledge
and wisdom because of their age, but also specifically people that really,
you know, not everybody that's older, just specifically people that have that
sense of, you know, particular like, you know, authority or knowledge. So
that's what sort of we're doing by combining the two. But you're
right, part of the idea of being older is people have life
experience, life wisdom, and that demands respect. So that's what we're going
to get to. Okay, the גמרא Gemara is going to particularly draw
that out by איסי בן יהודה. Okay, but I think that that's
a nice point to bring up now, right? Because if your basic
fundamental lens is, you know, oh, it's all about just how much
תורה Torah you know, right? So then, you know, that sounds a
little bit like how the גמרא Gemara is reading רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yose HaGlili bracketing תוספות, Tosafot, right? But what, you know, combining
the two like the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is sort of saying
a combination of that life experience and wisdom combined with the תורה
Torah authority, right? And that is what you're getting from the תנא
קמא. Tanna Kamma. The question then is, what about just the the
life experience without the תורה Torah knowledge? So that we'll get to.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. The תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma מאי טעמא? Mai Ta'ama? What's the reason of the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma that drives the position that you have to be both?
אי סלקא דעתך כדאמר רבי יוסי הגלילי, Ee salka da'atach k'de'amar Rabbi
Yose HaGlili, if it's like רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili said,
that זקן is totally independent of שיבה, אם
כן נכתוב רחמנא, Im kein nictov Rachmana, let the תורה Torah write
מפני שיבה תקום והדרת, so for the שיבה you should rise and
show respect, תקום והדרת פני זקן, Takum v'hadarta p'nei zaken, and rise
and show respect to the elder. Meaning if it really was two
fundamentally different categories. ומידי דלא כתב הכי, U'midei d'lo katav hachi, since
it didn't say that and it used sort of the same verbs
to refer to both of them, שמע מינה חד הוא, Shma mina
chad hu, fundamentally it's one category: older and a sage. Okay, אמר
מר, Amar Mar, so you have these three possibilities, right? Older and
a sage, older or a sage, or and, you know, and then,
you know, or just older although it doesn't seem that anybody says
just older. But at least תוספות Tosafot has a middle position, which
is, you know, older plus a little bit of a sage, you
know, a somewhat middle position תוספות Tosafot is working with. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר מר, Amar Mar, יכול
יהדרנו בממון, Yachol yehadreno b'mamon, maybe the הידור is something like lavishing
the person with gifts? תלמוד לומר, תקום והדרת. מה קימה שאין בה
חסרון כיס אף הידור שאין בו חסרון כיס. Mah kima she'ein bah
chissaron kis af hiddur she'ein bo chissaron kis. The same way rising
up doesn't cost you money, so it's a הידור that doesn't cost
you money. So the גמרא Gemara says, וקימה לית בה חסרון כיס?
V'kima leit beih chissaron kis? Who told you that rising up doesn't
cost money? מי לא עסקינן, Mi lo askinan, are we not talking
about a case דקנקיב מרגניתא, D'kanakiv marganita, there you are, you're making
holes in pearls, you're, you know, you're doing some very,
you know, some type of a job that that you get a
very large salary for, very large hourly salary
for, ואדהכי והכי וקאי מקמיה, V'adahachi v'hachi v'ka'ei mikamei, for that you
have to go and stop what you're doing and stand up, you
know? And maybe, you know, you're very much in a, you know,
in a particular zone and it takes you a lot of time
to reorient yourself and whatever it would
be, ובטיל ממלאכתו, U'vatil mimlachto, and then there's going to be an
actual cost, you're going to lose, you know, 20 minutes of your
salary, which might be a lot of money. So who says that
the קימה does not come with a expense to it and a
cost to it? So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא הקיש קימה להידור.
Ela hekesh kima l'hiddur. Here's how we know it. We start by
linking קימה to honor.
מה הידור שאין בו ביטול אף קימה שאין בה ביטול. Mah hiddur
she'ein bo bitul af kima she'ein bah bitul. So ביטול, Bitul, so
the rising would be a rising that does not interrupt with your
work. Now again, I don't know how we know that acts of
honor don't make you have to stop the work that you're doing,
but at least it's not a particular physical activity. Somebody's walking by,
you could verbally say something to them to show them respect that
might not cause you to stop your work. But anyway, somehow the
גמרא Gemara takes that as its point of departure. הידור, maybe it
might cost you money if it means lavishing gifts, but it doesn't
mean stopping to do the work that you're in the middle of.
So קימה doesn't mean stopping to do the work in the middle
of. So actually the הלכה is going to emerge that if you're
in the middle of working, you don't have to stop working to
rise up for somebody. Okay, and maybe you understand that it's not
considered to be a disrespect. It's clear to everyone the reason you're
not getting up is because you've got, you know, you're in the
middle of sawing a piece of wood or whatever, you know, you've
got, you know, or you're underneath the sink, you know, removing the,
you know, fixing the plumbing, and that's nobody thinks it's disrespectful that
you didn't get out of your fixing of the plumbing to stand
up for this person, right? So it's that—it's not just that it
shouldn't come at a cost to you, it's also that in that
sense of... context the lack of standing is not an act of
disrespect. So that's the first thing we conclude, that you don't have
to stand if it's going to cause you to stop your work.
Okay, and then the next step is oh so therefore standing never
costs you any money, so הידור never costs you any money. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מה הידור שאין בו ביטול
אף קימה שאין בו ביטול, Ma hiddur she'ein bo bittul af kima
she'ein bo bittul, the same way הידור you don't stop your work,
קימה you don't stop your work. ואקישנא הידור לקימה, Ve'akishana hiddur lekima,
and
then we go in the reverse order. נעשית קימה שאין בה חסרון
כיס. Na'asit kima she'ein ba chisron kis. Now that you don't have
to stand in order to stop your work, so standing doesn't cost
you money. אף הידור שאין בה חסרון כיס. Af hiddur she'ein ba
chisron kis. The way you honor is without is not an הידור
that shows money, so it does not mean lavish gifts, just other
maybe verbal forms of honoring, it is not something about like spending
money and giving gifts. מכאן אמרו, Mikan amru, and based on this
they said, אין בעלי אומניות רשאין לעמוד מפני תלמידי חכמים בשעה שעוסקים
במלאכתן. Ein baalei ummaniyot rashain laamod mipnei talmidei chachamim beshaah sheoskim bemlachtan.
People that are craftsmen are not allowed, I'll get back to the
word, to stand in front of תורה Torah sages when they are
involved in their work. Now the תוספות Tosfot asks: What do you
mean they're not allowed? It should say they're not required to. It
doesn't mean they're not allowed. So תוספות Tosfot has two explanations: either
we're talking about they're working for other people and therefore they're not
allowed because they're stealing labor from their boss, but if so that's
a very different point than the point we were making before. So
תוספות Tosfot other explanation is that sometimes רשאין rashain does not mean
allowed, sometimes רשאין rashain means required. And he says the better read
is that this just means they're not required to stand, okay, when
they are involved in their work. All right, yes.
Now I would imagine that because of that, if my interpretation is
correct, then it's even if that standing wouldn't cost them any money.
Fundamentally it's not about they're not required that their standing come at
some personal expense. What it really is is that if you're עוסק
במלאכתן, osek bemlachtan, it's not a context in which standing is expected,
right? I mean, you don't agree?
Certainly because let's say you're working for somebody else, so there are
things that you're supposed to do even on the boss's time, you
stop and retrieve and say קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema and שמונה עשרה.
Shmoneh Esrei. So you know, maybe this is something that this could
be defined as something that you have to do even though it's
on someone else's
time.
Right, so that's what I was thinking that the concern here isn't,
well first of all it's not only limited to the case of
a boss, mean those are the two readings of תוספות, Tosfot, but
I was saying like even if,
even if it's not going to be at an expense to the
boss, even if it's not going to be an expense to you,
you're doing your own work. Okay, I don't know, you're in the
middle of hammering away at you're building some cabinet, okay? And if
you stop now and show honor, whatever, then you can, it's not
like you're going to lose a total amount because you'll just make
up the time later, right? So we're not talking about there's going
to be any real loss of money. But nevertheless, is that a
context in which there's an expectation in the middle of banging away
at building the cabinet, that you know, oh you're disrespecting me you
didn't stop your work to stand because I walked into the room,
right? That's sort of the way I read it, that in the
end the גמרא Gemara learns from it the question about
חסרון כיס, but I think the logic for it is one more
about whether it's a context in which standing should
be
expected. Okay, anyway, I don't know. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Where are we? Okay.
ולא, Velo,
is that really they do not have to? והתנן, Vehatan, don't we
teach in a משנה, Mishna, כל בעלי אומניות עומדים מפניהם ושואלים בשלומם,
Kol baalei ummaniyot omdim mipneihem veshoalim bishlomam,
when the people who are bringing ביכורים Bikkurim come to ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
all the crafts people stand up when they walk into the, when
they come by and they ask about their wellbeing, ואומרים להם, Veomrim
lahem, and they say to them, אחינו אנשי מקום פלוני, Acheinu anshei
makom ploni, our brethren from such and such a place, you came
all the way from יריחו Yericho or from France or wherever you
came from, בואכם לשלום, Boachem leshalom, come in peace, it's so wonderful
to have you here in ירושלים Yerushalayim bringing your ביכורים. Bikkurim. So
you see that you have to interrupt your crafts in order to
do that type of a greeting, so presumably also
when a זקן walks in, a sage walks in. אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan, מפניהם עומדים מפני תלמידי חכמים אין עומדים. Mipneihem omdim
mipnei talmidei chachamim ein omdim. Correct, you stand up before the people
who bring ביכורים, Bikkurim, and you don't stand up before the תורה
Torah sage when you're עוסק במלאכתן. osek bemlachtan. So what's the difference?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי יוסי בר אבין, Amar Rabbi
Yose bar Avin, בוא ראה כמה חביבה מצוה בשעתה. Bo reeh kamma
chaviva mitzvah beshaatah. Look, this shows you how great is a מצוה
mitzvah done. In its right time. שהרי מפניהם עומדים, sheharei mipnehem omdim,
מפני תלמידי חכמים אין עומדים. mipnei talmidei chachamim ein omdim. Here are
people that are doing מצוה mitzvah in a very special time, this
is the right time to be doing it, it doesn't come at
every opportunity, it's a special opportunity, and you show particular respect to
this performance of a מצוה, mitzvah, more respect than you show to
a Torah sage. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait, there's a different
reason why that case would be special. ודילמא שאני התם, V'dilma shani
hatam, maybe that case is special not because it's מצוה בשעתה, mitzvah
b'shatah, but דאם כן אתה מכשילן לעתיד לבוא, de'im ken ata machshilan
l'atid lavo, because if you don't show them welcoming and warmth and
respect when they come, they're going to say, I can't believe it,
I schlepped all the way from יריחו Yericho to ירושלים Yerushalayim to
bring my ביכורים bikurim and everybody was so rude to me. I
walked through a town, nobody stopped to say hello, it was clear
I'd been traveling for a while, right? So next time, who's going
to want to schlep to ירושלים Yerushalayim to bring your ביכורים? bikurim?
Okay, so it's a very practical reason. And anyway, but one way
or the other, it's a special case. Okay, so you don't have
to interrupt your מלאכה. melacha.
אמר מר, Amar mar, now let's go back and look at what
we said before. יכול יעמוד מפניו מבית הכסא ומבית המרחץ. Yachol ya'amod
mipanav mibeit hakisei umibeit hamerchatz. There you are in the bathhouse or
sitting on the toilet and a זקן walks in, maybe you have
to interrupt what you're doing and stand up? So the גמרא Gemara,
says ולא, v'lo, are you telling me you don't have to?
For רבי חייא הוי יתיב בי מסותא, Rabbi Chiya hava yativ bei
masuta, וחליף ואזיל רבי שמעון ברבי, v'chalif v'azil Rabbi Shimon berabi, and
Rabbi Shimon the son of Rebbe, so that was a case also
he was a נשיא, or the son of a נשיא, ולא קם
מקמיה, v'lo kam mikamei, and he didn't stand up in the presence
of Rabbi Shimon when he was in the bathhouse. ואיקפד, V'ikpad, and
Rabbi Shimon was upset, ואתא אמר ליה לאבוהי, v'ata amar lei l'avuhi,
he went to tell his father Rebbe and he said to him,
I can't believe this, שני חומשים שניתי לו בספר תהלים, shnei chumashim
shaniti lo b'sefer tehillim, I taught him two-fifths or two of the
חומשים chumashim of ספר תהלים, sefer tehillim, I'll get back to that
in a minute, ולא עמד מפני, v'lo amad mipanai, and he didn't
stand in my presence, which by the way is very interesting, which
is what type of a sage demands standing in the presence, because
until now we've been talking about objectively a Torah sage, somebody who's
objectively a Torah sage. Now we're talking about somebody who has taught
you Torah. I taught him, I'm his Rebbe. And also this gets
to that משנה mishnah in פרקי אבות, pirkei avot, which is somebody
who even teaches something, האיר עיניו ואפילו משנה אחת, he'ir einav v'afilu
mishna achat, even if somebody just teaches you just one idea, they're
your Rebbe and you call them רבי אלופי ומיודעי, Rabbi alufi u'miyuda'i,
you show them all these forms of respect. So he says, okay,
he taught him what, two-fifths of תהלים? Tehillim? What did he do?
He taught him when he was a kid how to read פסוקים?
pesukim? Did he teach him מדרשים? midrashim? I mean what level? It's
not like we're not talking about great Torah scholarship, it doesn't seem
like. And nevertheless, I taught him something, he needs to stand before
me. So it's very interesting here that it focuses in on the
רבי תלמיד Rebbe talmid relationship and even again that just teaching a
small amount, it seems like, or nothing that's necessarily super high level,
is enough to demand this respect. So I can't, so that's very
important. So anyway, back to our point about the bathhouse, he says
I can't believe he didn't stand before me. Okay. ותו, V'tu, and
another case, בר קפרא ואמרי לה רבי שמואל בר רבי יוסי, Bar
Kappara v'amrei lah Rabbi Shmuel bar Rabbi Yossi, Bar Kappara and some
say Rabbi Shmuel bar Rabbi Yossi, הוו יתבי בי מסותא, havu yatvei
bei masuta, they were sitting in the bathhouse, וחלף ואזיל רבי שמעון
ברבי, v'chalaf v'azil Rabbi Shimon berabi, the same Rabbi Shimon berabi was
passing by, ולא קמו מקמיה, v'lo kamu mikamei, they didn't stand in
the presence of. ואיקפד, V'ikpad, he got upset, ואתא אמר ליה לאבוהי,
v'ata amar lei l'avuhi, he said to his father Rebbe and he
said to him, I can't believe this, שני שלישי שליש שניתי לו
בתורת כהנים, shnei shelishi shelish shaniti lo b'torat kohanim, I taught him
two-thirds of a third of the ספרא, Sifra, of תורת כהנים. Torat
Kohanim. Okay, two-ninths I guess. But anyway, apparently תורת כהנים Torat Kohanim
was divided into thirds and I taught him two-thirds of one section
of תורת כהנים, Torat Kohanim, which is at least tannaitic material, okay.
ולא עמד מפני, v'lo amad mipanai, and he didn't rise up in
front of me. ואמר לו, V'amar lo, so the father said to
him, שמא בהן יושב ומהרהר. shema bahen yoshev u'meharher. You know what?
Maybe the reason they didn't stand before you is that they were,
they were חזרing chozer what they had just learned from you. So
it was like they were so distracted by the Torah that was
going through their head, they didn't realize you were passing by. But
of course he said it in a way like it's דווקא davka
because of your Torah that you taught them, that's why they were
so distracted and they were thinking about it that they didn't realize
you were there and they didn't stand up before you. Okay. So
anyway, the גמרא Gemara says טעמא דבהן יושב ומהרהר, ta'ama d'bahen yoshev
u'meharher, Rebbe's defense of them was only that they were maybe too
their thoughts were too involved in the Torah that they were thinking
about. הא לאו הכי, Ha lav hachi, if it would not have
been for that, לא, they would have acted incorrectly. But הא בית
המרחץ, ha beit hamerchatz, you don't have to show respect in a
bathhouse? So the גמרא Gemara says no, לא קשיא, Lo kashya, הא
בבתי גואי הא בבתי ברא. ha b'vatei gavai ha b'vatei barai. The
question is, are we talking about the outer house of the bathhouse
or the inner section? Right, the inner part is where everybody is
naked. Where everybody is naked, everybody is fundamentally equal. In that context,
there's no idea of showing respect. It's not like a social context
in which respect, that type of respect for
status is not appropriate. I mean basic human respect is necessary but
the respect for status is not appropriate. So that's in the inner
bathhouse. In the outer part where people are sitting half clothed or
whatever it might be, that's where it is appropriate still to show
respect. Okay, and that's where this was taking place. And the גמרא
Gemara says הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistabra, that actually makes sense
that they were in the outer room. דאמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן. d'amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan. בכל
מקום bechol makom מותר mutar להרהר leharhor חוץ chutz מבית המרחץ mi'Beis
ha'Merchatz ובית הכסא. u'Beis ha'Kisei. So how else were they thinking in
תורה? Torah What was רבי'ס Rebbe's response? Oh, they were thinking in
תורה. Torah How would they be thinking in תורה Torah, if they
were in the inner room and they were naked? So clearly the
whole event took place in the outer room and that's why he
was expecting some respect. So גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא לאונסא שאני.
dilma le'unsa shani. You know what, maybe they were in the inner
room and they still maybe sometimes your head is so involved in
what you've been learning and thinking about that you can't stop yourself
thinking in תורה Torah. even when you're in the bathroom and you
can't stop
yourself even when you go into the inner room of the bathhouse.
So the fact that רבי Rebbe, said maybe they were thinking about
תורה Torah doesn't prove that they were in the outer room. They
could have been in the inner room and רבי Rebbe? could have
said they can't help their thoughts, they're so involved in the תורה
Torah, that they've been learning. Okay, but anyway what's fascinating about this
is a besides reiterating the point about the bathhouse as a place
you don't
show respect but you don't have the need of respect for these
social status is the idea that we now have the רבי Rebbe
idea, the זקן idea specifically in a רב תלמיד rav talmid relationship
and again even around something that's not the most intense or form
of
תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, not something like your רבו המובהק. Rabbo ha'Muvhak.
It's sort of like your רבי המלמדו דבר אחד Rebbe ha'melamdo davar
echad type of a model. By the way, an interesting parenthetical point
about what's שני חומשים shnei chumashim in ספר תהלים. Sefer Tehillim. Look
at this תוספות. Tosafos. שני חומשים. shnei chumashim. תוספות Tosafos says פירש
בקונטרס לשון חומש, perish be'kuntres lashon chomesh, a fifth of הספר, ha'sefer,
so it means two fifths of ספר תהלים. Sefer Tehillim. ויש מפרשים
חמישה חומשים יש בו. v'yesh mefarshim chamisha chumashim yesh bo. Now the
same way the תורה has five books which we call חומשים, chumashim,
there are five books of ספר תהלים, Sefer Tehillim, five חומשים. chumashim.
Okay, what do you know? כמו בשל תורה. kemo beshel Torah. אשרי
האיש, ashrei ha'ish, it starts with תהלים פרק א Tehillim Perek Aleph
is book number one. כאיל תערוג על אפיקי מים ke'ayal ta'arog al
afikei mayim פרק מ"ב Perek Mem Beis
begins book number two. אך טוב לישראל ach tov le'Yisrael פרק ע"ג
Perek Ayin Gimmel is book number three. תפילה למשה Tefilla le'Moshe צ'
Tzadik is book number
four. יאמרו גאולי yomru ge'ulei is קז Kof Zayin is book number
five. Now how does תוספות Tosafos know to divide it in those
ways? So תוספות Tosafos says listen to this: ולכל אחד מן הספרים
אלו מסיים באמן. u'lechol echad min ha'sefarim elu mesayem be'Amen. At the
end of each one of those sections there's the word אמן, Amen,
right, at the end, לבד מן האחרון שהוא סוף תהלים levad min
ha'acharon she'hu sof Tehillim not at the very end of the last
one because that's the end of תהלים, Tehillim, you don't need a
word to break it up. But actually there are, I don't know,
I didn't do a Bar-Ilan search, I don't know if there are
only four אמנים Amens in ספר תהלים Sefer Tehillim but it is
why, of why one תהלים Tehillim ends with אמן Amen and nothing
else does. So תוספות: Tosafos: the אמן Amen isn't the end of
that פרק, perek, it's the end of a whole section. And so
you actually see תהלים Tehillim is broken up into five sections, very
interesting.
Sounds related to probably to why we say in פסוקי דזמרה Pesukei
d'Zimra when we finish the end of those תהלים, Tehillim, the end
of the last הללויה Hallelujah we
say ברוך ה' לעולם אמן ואמן,
Baruch Hashem
l'olam
Amen v'Amen, right, as a way of sort of showing a conclusion,
yes. So somebody can now do a Bar-Ilan search and see how,
if there's more than just those four אמנים Amens in ספר תהלים.
Sefer Tehillim. Okay, so now the גמרא continues.
יכול יעצים עיניו כמי שלא רואהו, yachol ya'atzim einav k'mi she'lo ro'eihu,
maybe you should close your eyes and pretend you don't see the,
you know, your רבי Rebbe and you don't have to stand. So
the גמרא says what? אטו ברשיעי עסקינן? atu be'rashiei askinan? Are we
talking about wicked people? Like your רבי Rebbe. enters the room, you
have a חיוב chiyuv to stand. So what? So maybe you're just
going to pretend you're not obligated. So why do I need a
פסוק to tell me that you can't try to fool people and
get out of an obligation that you have? So the גמרא says
no, אלא כי יכול יעצים עיניו מקמי דלימטי זמן חיובא, ela ki
yachol ya'atzim einav mikamei d'limtei zman chiyuva,
maybe what you should do is close your eyes
before the time of obligation comes, meaning you see, you know your
רבי'ס Rebbe's going to be coming into this room any minute. You
hear him in the hallway outside the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. So
what you do is you situate yourself in the בית מדרש Beis
Medrash in a place where you're not, can't, don't have a line
of sight so when he walks into the room you won't be
seeing him and you won't have a חיוב chiyuv to stand. So
technically you're not obligated because you actually technically did not see him
enter the room. Okay, so in that case תלמוד לומר תקום ויראת.
Talmud lomar takum ve-yareta No,
you have to fear God so you have to, you cannot sort
of manipulate it so and obviously because since you know he's entering
the room, I mean it actually raises an interesting question which is:
Did you really get out of the obligation? Is really, like I
don't know, if a blind person knows that their רבי Rebbe has
entered without seeing it, he's presumably still חייב. chayav. The awareness, right,
is presumably enough without the seeing, right? So is it that you
maybe but so is the problem here that you didn't really get
out of the obligation? Or is it that no, technically you did
get out of the obligation but you're not allowed to manipulate it
so that you get out of the obligation?
Reminds me of that earlier story with it's when the person hears
his mother's
footsteps, oh
right, he says דשכינה קאתי de'Shechinah ka'asi and he's preparing and here
it's like avoiding. That's a nice contrast, right. Okay. דכי מטא זמן
חיובא de'ki mata zman chiyuva
so you would manipulate it so that when the time of obligation
comes לא חזי ליה lo chazi lei דקאי קמיה dekai kamei that
you should have to rise up. תלמוד לומר תקום ויראת. Talmud lomar
takum ve-yareta, תנא. tanna. תלמוד לומר תקום ויראת Talmud lomar takum ve-yareta
teaches you that you have to fear God in your standing, you
can't manipulate the situation. Okay. תנא איזהו קימה שיש בה הידור, Tanna
eizehu kima she-yesh bah hiddur, what is a type of, I'm sorry,
תלמוד לומר תקום ויראת, takum v'yareisa. that's the end of the previous
one. תלמוד לומר תקום ויראת teaches you that you have to fear
God in your standing, you can't manipulate the situation. Okay. תנא איזהו
קימה שיש בה הידור, Tanna eizehu kima she-yesh bah hiddur, what's a
rising that shows honor? הוי אומר זה ארבע אמות, Havei omer ze
arba amot, rising up within four אמות. amot. Right then somebody's right
there and you show them and like you're connecting to them in
your rising. Right, it's not just, you know, what?
Like within four אמות amot of them? Of you.
No, no, no, within four אמות amot of you. So if they're
at the opposite end of the room, presumably there's two things that's
accomplished when they're closer to you. If they're at the opposite end
of the room, it's not as obvious that you're rising because of
them. And when you're, so A, when they're in your zone it's
clear it's because of them, and also when you rise in their
presence it's a way of giving them directly that respect, right, you're
showing it, you know, directly to them. So therefore it's within the
ארבע אמות. arba amot, Okay, so אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לא אמרן
אלא ברבו שאינו
מובהק. lo amran ella be-rabbo she-eino muvhak.
This is only by the master who's not your like prime teacher,
your, your, I always say expert, but expert doesn't, isn't the right
word. Anyway, your, you know, your primary teacher. אבל ברבו מובהק, Aval
be-rabbo muvhak, the one who is your primary teacher, מלא עיניו, melo
einav, as long as he's within eyesight. Now this I find fascinating
because, you know, we just got saying that the true הידור comes
when they're in your space, that actually it's not as much of
an act of respect when they're far away. So why? But on
the other hand it's like, you know, there's the opposite argument which
is, if my רבי Rebbe is anywhere nearby, if I can even
see my רבי, Rebbe how could I remain seated as I'm seeing
my רבי? Rebbe, So the act of rising in a way, you
know, is not as much, doesn't show as much direct respect because
it's not clear, as clearly connected, but it's like I can't not
be standing if, you know, if he's anywhere within my eyesight. So
it's interesting, you sort of lose the power of the act of
rising for the need to be standing when he is, you know,
you know, the, but the act itself is not, so it's just
this interesting thing. So we're going to see that part of it
is also that you don't get to sit down until he leaves
completely from your eye, so you remain standing. So you know, the
act itself might not be the immediate same degree of showing of
respect, but the remaining standing until he's out of your eyesight is
also part of it. Yes.
Interesting dynamic between the honor you're according him and the מדה middah
you're cultivating within yourself.
Ah,
that's interesting. So like what, what, ah. So, so,
and, and why more that מדה middah in the case of your
רבי rather than in
you,
you mean just because like what would it mean that I've received
so much from him?
Exactly the act of standing when he's
half a block away.
Right, right, right. When you stand within ארבע אמות, arba amot that's
clearly directed towards him.
Right, right, right. But the other one is, but if I've received
so much from him, what would it mean for me, right, that's
an interesting way of framing it. What would it mean for me
in this context not to be able, not to be responding? To
know he's around and for me not to be responding, that's a
very nice way, yes.
And there might also, I don't know if there's an aspect of
like, recognize your רבי is
from farther away also, right? Oh, that's interesting.
Someone who's a, and like they might not know that you're standing
for them because they don't know you and they don't know that
you know them and like, but it makes more
sense that that rising is for them once that connection exists. So
right, where he knows who
you are and knows why you're standing in your life.
Oh, that's an interesting thought. That's an interesting thought. Like you see
a friend that you know from across the block, like yeah, exactly,
yeah, because if you don't wave it's like what, he doesn't recognize
me or whatever. Right, right, right.
That's an interesting thought too. Okay, those are really interest, good thoughts.
Okay. So now the גמרא says like this.
Okay. אביי
מכי
הוה חזי ליה לאודנא דחמרא דרב יוסף דאתי, Abaye miki hava chazi
lei le-udna de-chamra de-Rav Yosef de-ati, when אביי Abaye would see the
ear of the donkey of רב יוסף Rav Yosef came into his
field of vision, so he so much recognized him, he recognized his
donkey's ear, הוה קאי, hava kai, he would stand up. Okay, that's
how careful he was about his רבי. אביי הוה רכיב חמרא, Abaye
hava rachiv chamra, now אביי Abaye himself was riding a donkey וקמסגי
אגודא דנהרא ve-ka-masgi aguda de-nahara and he was walking on the like
the riverbank, סגי, sagi, and he was walking and he was like
riding along on the riverbank, excuse me, יתבי רב משרשיא ורבנן באידך
גיסא, yatvi Rav Mesharshiya ve-rabbanan be-idach gissa, רב משרשיא Rav Mesharshiya and
other rabbis were on the other side of the river ולא קמו
מקמיה ve-lo kamu mikamei and they didn't stand up when they saw
אביי Abaye on his side of the river.
He wasn't in their ארבע אמות but he was in their eyesight.
אמר להו Amar lehu ולאו רבו מובהק אנא, ve-lav rabbo muvhak ana,
I don't understand, I'm not your, I'm not your primary teacher? How
did you not stand? אמרו ליה Amru lei לאו אדעתין, lav ada-tin,
they said to him,
you're right, we weren't paying attention. Okay, which actually does point out
an interesting thing because if somebody isn't immediately, immediately in your zone,
you doesn't, you're not necessarily aware when they're, you know, even if
they're in my, technically they're in my eyesight, but it could be
I to some degree see who you are, but I'm not registering
it because, you know, my focus is in another. is right now
about this picnic we're having, so I'm not like fully registering what's
going on on the other side, right? But anyway, so that's part
of the challenge here, maybe part of the message also is is
that, you know, you have it has to be אדעתיה, adaatiah, like
if you see your Rebbe even far away, that's part of the
כבוד is that you is that you, you know, it makes an
impression on you even if you're at a distance and doing something
else. Okay, so now the Gemara says like this: רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, מנין לזקן שלא יטריח? minayin
lezaken shelo yatriach? תלמוד לומר זקן ויראת. The end of this ברייתא,
how do you know not to core— put a weight on other
people? So you have to do your own to to not, you
know, to minimize people's respect obligation, which is not the same as
being מוחל on the כבוד, but avoiding circumstances as we'll see. אמר
אביי, amar Abaye, again, Abaye has a lot to say about this
סוגיא. sugya. נקטינן, naktinan, we take the position דמאקיף חיי, demakif chaye,
that if you go around so you don't have to go into
a place where a lot of people are and force them to
stand for you, you take a, you know, you take a detour
to avoid that, you'll live a long life, you know, that's a
very good thing. So again, it's interesting, Abaye, and now we're going
to have a story about Abaye himself. Right, the same Abaye who
was upset that his students didn't stand at the opposite side of
the river, it's not like Abaye was going around demanding and being
מקפיד makpid on his כבוד, because here's the next story.
אביי מאקיף, Abaye makif, Abaye would go around places where he knew
that there were people that would rise up before him. He didn't
want to you know, put himself in situations where people had to
stand for him. Okay, so רבי זירא מאקיף, Rabbi Zeira makif, Rabbi
Zeira would go around. רבינא הוה יתיב קמיה דרב ירמיה מדיפתי, Ravina
hava yativ kammei deRav Yirmeya miDiphti, Ravina was sitting in front of
Rav Yirmeya from Diphti. חלף ההוא גברא קמיה ולא מיכסי רישיה. chalaf
hahu gavra kammei velo michassi reisheh. So since we talk about passing
by somebody, so here's another story which is not exactly related, but
anyway, a certain person was passing by and he didn't have his
head covered. Once again with the head covering, right? We've had that
before. אמר כמה חציף האי גברא, amar kama chatzif hai gavra, how
חוצפהדיק chutzpadik does this person have that he's walking in the presence
of rabbis and he's not covering his head? So אמר ליה דילמא
ממתא מחסיא ניהו דגיסי ברבנן. amar lei dilma mimata mechasya nihu degissi
berabbanan. Maybe he's from this place of Mata Mechasya that they are
very sort of comfortable terms with their rabbis and therefore they haven't
learned to cover their head in the presence of their rabbis. So
this is a very interesting גמרא, like what's the גמרא exactly getting
at? Right, so one wonders if like, you know, why is this
story relevant?
So I mean you could say it's a combination that הידור is
not just rising up, right? That's what we've been focused, קימה is
rising up. הידור is other ways of showing respect, so maybe under
certain societal norms the way of showing respect is you have your
head covered in the presence of a rabbi. And here saying, you
know, in this society they don't do that. But I think that
the other point is exactly this tension where that I've been talking
about about being מוחל on your כבוד, which the גמרא was conflicted
about, and not putting people in unnecessary circumstances to show you כבוד.
So this society, the rabbis basically were מוחל on their כבוד. It's
okay, you can have your head uncovered in my presence. And that's
not such a good thing, right? Because then you maybe don't learn
to show the respect that's due to rabbis and then you go
to another society and it's it's seen as an affront, right? Another
type of a community. So there's I think a like a little
I to me I hear like a little criticism, you know, you
know, maybe you hear something else, maybe you hear oh, it's okay,
you know, the rabbis in that community are all right with it.
I don't know, I hear a little criticism, I hear a difference
between being מוחל on your כבוד and like no. When אביי Abaye
was walking and there were students and they weren't showing him his
כבוד, he was מקפיד. makpid. You guys have to show me the
כבוד, but that doesn't mean I go around asking for it. I
actually try to avoid it. But when we're in those circumstances, I'm
not מוחל, you need to show respect that's part of כבוד התורה.
kevod hatorah. So I think it's that interesting balance between being מוחל
and letting somebody get away with not showing respect as opposed to
not trying to, you know, trying to avoid situations which makes people
have to show the respect. Yes.
How would a family member be supposed to act?
So we're going to get to that. Like a father and a
son or whatever. Okay, let's try to just turn the page. I
know it's already 8:30, but I just we I need to be
not more than one עמוד behind. Okay, so the גמרא says like
this: איסי בן יהודה אומר מפני שיבה תקום ואפילו כל שיבה במשמע,
Issi ben Yehuda omer mipnei seiva takum vaafilu kol seiva bemashma, any
elderly person, right? Not only a sage. אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כאיסי
בן יהודה. amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha keIssi ben Yehuda. We rule like
that. So that's important. Included in respect is respect for old age.
So the גמרא says רבי יוחנן הוה קאי מקמי סבי דארמאי. Rabbi
Yochanan hava kai mikamei sabei de'armai. Rabbi Yochanan would get up in
front of old non-Jews, right? The Arameans, meaning not only a not
only a Jew, any old person. אמר כמה הרפתקי עדו עלייהו דהני.
amar kama harpatkei adu alaiahu dehanei.
How many like life events, life circumstances have passed over this person?
Right? So the very fact of the wisdom and experience and travails
that a person has has has has has endured, you know, through
their life, that itself, that age and that life experience demands respect.
Very powerful statement. רבא מקיים לא קאי. Rava mikkam lo kai. Now
interestingly, though Rava... רבא Rava would not rise up. Maybe he felt
that that would compromise his תורה honor, you know, that it is
true, there is a reality of life experience, but that doesn't mean
that a תורה sage rises up to somebody who that's all they
have is just that life experience. So he himself wouldn't rise up.
מיקם לא קאי, mikam lo kai, חיזור עביד ליה. chizur avid leh.
He would do some form of respect. According to רש"י, that would
be the lifting himself a little bit off the chair. Okay, אביי
יהיב ידא לסבא. Abaye yahiv yada lesaba. אביי Abaye would have, give
his hand to an older person, you know, he'd have an older
person lean on him, he'd help the older person cross the street.
He would show this respect and give this own personal service, this
big תורה sage. רבא, Rava, now again, רבא Rava did not go
that far, he was trying to balance it with תורה honor apparently,
and משדר שלוחיה. meshader shluchei. He'd have his servant help out the
old person, but he wouldn't do it himself, right? So it's an
interesting balance that we're trying to strike. רב נחמן משדר גוזאי. Rav
Nachman meshader guzzei. רב נחמן Rav Nachman would also send some of
his attendants. אמר אי לאו תורה, Amar ilav Torah, if it were
not for my תורה, כמה נחמן בר אבא איכא בשוקא. kamma Nachman
bar Abba ika bashuka. There's a lot of נחמנס Nachmans that are
out there. So what, I'm just like any other נחמן? Nachman? Everybody
has to show respect to an older person, but I also represent
תורה. So I can't compromise the תורה that I represent, because at
the end of the day, that is something that demands more respect
than just old age. So it's very fascinating. On the one hand,
we're saying old age on its own does demand respect in terms
of wisdom and life experiences, but that's not at the same level
of תורה, so does that mean that nevertheless you should be מוחל
on your תורה כבוד, Torah kavod, going back to that issue and
show respect to, you know, and do it yourself, or do you
find some type of a balance, which is what רבא Rava is
finding. אמר רב איבו, Amar Rav Aivo, now we'll just turn the
page, אמר רב ינאי, Amar Rav Yannai, אין תלמיד
חכם רשאי לעמוד מפני רבו אלא שחרית וערבית כדי שלא יהא כבודו
מרובה מכבוד שמים. ein talmid chacham rashai la'amod mipnei rabbo ella shacharit
ve'arvit kedei shelo yehei kevodo merubbeh mikivod shamayim. That you do not,
you're not allowed to, or תוספות Tosafot says you don't have to,
stand up for your רבי more than twice a day, because you
only pray to God, right, well, I mean, you pray to God
three times a day, but presumably he's talking about כבוד שמים kevod
shamayim is presumably קריאת שמע. Keriat Shema. Okay, so therefore, you know,
you don't have to do more than you'd, I mean רש"י says,
אין
מקב... שפני יוצרו אינו מקבל אלא שחרית וערבית. ein mekab... shepnei yotzro
eino mekabbel ella shacharit ve'arvit. Again, I don't know what that means,
because there's also מנחה, Mincha, unless we're talking about קריאת שמע. Keriat
Shema. Okay, but to some degree, you know, you do, maybe it
just means you דאוון, daven, you know, if you דאוון מנחה daven
Mincha and מעריב Ma'ariv at the same time, so you have דאוונינג
davening in the morning and the דאוונינג davening at the end of
the day. Okay, so anyway, so you don't have to show more
respect to your רבי more than you do to God. Now the
question is, does that mean just because if your רבי is around
the whole time, like if you're in the same ישיבה with your
רבי, like it's like if there's a lightning storm, how many times
are you going to make the ברכה bracha on lightning, right? So
that might be the context as opposed to if somebody is, drops
by five times in the day, but you're not around them the
whole time, maybe you have to stand each time. But maybe it
means if there's a constant presence like with you and God, right,
then it's only morning and the evening and that frames the whole
day as a way of showing respect and not every time they
enter the room. Okay, so we'll pick up with that discussion tomorrow.